Guide to the Brooklyn Division of the Protestant Council of Churches records ARC.270
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Division of the Protestant Council of Churches records
1840-1979
1895-1974
Brooklyn Historical Society
Protestant Council of the City of New York. Brooklyn Division
ARC.270
18 Linear Feet in 28 manuscript boxes and eight custom ledger boxes.
The records of the Brooklyn Division of the Protestant Council of Churches trace the history of Protestantism and missionary work in Brooklyn well into the 20th century. The bulk of the collection consists of office files dating from 1950 to 1974; however, much of the material in this collection concerns missionary work at the turn of the 19th century, and the collection dates back to 1840. Included in the collection are minutes, subject files, publications, financial records, and newspaper clippings.
Historical Note
The Records of the Brooklyn Division of the Protestant Council of Churches offer the history of a century of Protestant organizations originating from the Brooklyn City Tract Society, which was founded as a branch of the American Tract Society in 1829 to "promote the interests of evangelical religion, by the systematic distribution within the bounds of [Brooklyn], of religious Tracts published by the American Tract Society: and to aid that Society, with all surplus funds, in extending its operations." Originally focusing on the dissemination of religious literature and scripture, the Society soon expanded to offer religious services, and employed missionaries to extend their work throughout the City of Brooklyn. The Society's name was changed in 1858 to The Brooklyn City Mission and Tract Society, and in the same year its constitution was amended to reflect this change.
The Society continued to prosper under its new name, employing both men and women as missionaries, and made active efforts to reach out to the underprivileged, including mothers and children, especially recent immigrants. Much of the Society's work focused upon the idea of "American Christianity" with the hope of turning its wards into devout Christians and "reliable and helpful citizens." Each missionary was charged with the task of visiting every tenement in his or her district, distributing literature, and, if welcomed, establishing neighborhood prayer meetings.
In 1886, the Woman's Branch of the Brooklyn City Mission and Tract Society was formally organized. Known as the Women's Auxiliary from 1887 on, this division coexisted alongside the Society and "was to supplement the work of The City Mission, by taking up mission work to be done in homes among women and children." All Christian women were encouraged to join the Auxiliary, not necessarily to work as missionaries, but to lend their prayers, influence, and financial support to the cause of missionary work.
The Society sponsored many activities aimed at drawing persons away from vices such as alcohol and gambling. Activities sponsored by the Society included lectures, prayer meetings, bible classes, and a sewing school. The Society founded a "Floating Bethel" in 1893. This boat/meeting house was removed from the brothels and taverns of the waterfront and provided a space where sailors could come to read, write, rest, and pray.
In addition, the Society worked to "rescue the perishing," primarily through its City Mission Night Shelter for Homeless Men, which provided food, shelter, aid in obtaining employment, and religious services. The Society itself offered employment to many, running a broom factory and chair caning facility. These successful business ventures helped defray the costs of the Society's charitable work.
As the Society continued to expand, it focused less on the dissemination of literature. Missionary work had become the Society's primary function, and by 1906 it operated 16 mission stations in Brooklyn. The Society chose to change its name accordingly in 1929 to the Brooklyn City Mission Society. The bylaws were also amended, declaring the Society's objective as being "to promote interdenominational missionary interests in the Borough of Brooklyn and to minister to the spiritual and material needs of the unfortunate." Shortly after this change in 1932, the Brooklyn City Mission Society took on the work of the Brooklyn Federation of Churches. The Federation had been established in 1920 to bring all Protestant denominations and races together in a cooperative effort to promote Christianity through religious education, social service, court work, and other venues. The two organizations had operated side by side for many years, sharing a Secretary, Dr. Frederick M. Gordon, from 1926 to 1932. The Society again changed its name, this time to the Brooklyn Church and Mission Federation. The bylaws of the Brooklyn City Mission Society were amended in accordance with the restructuring to declare a twofold object: 1) "to unite the Protestant Churches of Christ in Brooklyn for the prosecution of work that can better be done in union than in separation, and to secure a larger combined influence for the churches in all matters affecting the religious, moral and social welfare of the people, so as to promote the application of the law of Christ in every relation of human life," and 2) "to promote interdenominational missionary interests in the borough of Brooklyn, and to minister to the spiritual and material needs of the unfortunate."
The Federation continued to operate as such over the next decade, working throughout Brooklyn to reach out to a large, diverse, and changing community. With the Great Depression, the church had to rethink its mission, focusing more on service to the community and providing aid to those in need. Outreach during this time included mothers' clubs, boys' clubs, parole and court work, civic affairs conferences, industrial relations conferences, and population surveys. The Federation also began to focus on church unity, as it observed that cooperative efforts would "produce greater strength and a more definite program and positive results."
In June of 1946, the Federation "voted to amalgamate its program and activities with The Protestant Council of the City of New York to become the Brooklyn Division of the Council." Although the Brooklyn Church and Mission Federation was not officially dissolved, the organization was now widely known as the Brooklyn Division of the Protestant Council of Churches. As such, the organization further shifted its focus to church unity and the future survival of the Protestant Church.
With the demographic changes of the early and mid-20th century, the face of Brooklyn Protestantism had changed greatly. At the turn of the century, Protestants made up more than one-half of Brooklyn's population. By 1950, Protestant Brooklynites had dropped to 19.5 percent of the total population. The increase in immigration of non-Protestant groups and the movement of the population to the suburbs led to a major decrease in the population of the Division's traditional Brooklyn base of white Protestants. By the later half of the 20th century, Protestants had become a religious minority within both the Borough of Brooklyn and the City of New York, causing the church to reevaluate its position within the community. The Division expanded its field of social services to include work with veterans, hospital and jail chaplaincies, interracial projects, peace activities, and economic justice programs. As the Division moved its focus towards social service and away from direct mission work, it strove to identify the church as an indispensable part of the community. It strove to promote unification especially with the growing African American Protestant community that made up nearly one-half of Brooklyn's Protestant population by 1963. The Division continued for the remainder of the 20th century to use its influence as a united body within the community to strive for social reform to assist Brooklyn's ever changing population.
Sources:
Board of Directors' Minutes, April 3, 1929; Records of the Brooklyn Division of the Protestant Council of Churches; Library; The Brooklyn Historical Society.
"Brooklyn: A Working Document." 1968: 3-4; Records of the Brooklyn Division of the Protestant Council of Churches; Library; The Brooklyn Historical Society.
Brooklyn Church and Mission Federation: Report for the Year 1946: 1; Records of the Brooklyn Division of the Protestant Council of Churches; Library; The Brooklyn Historical Society.
Brooklyn City Tract Society Constitution, 1848; Records of the Brooklyn Division of the Protestant Council of Churches; Library; The Brooklyn Historical Society.
"The Church United Evolves." Brooklyn Eagle. 7 June 1938.
The City Mission and Tract Society Journal. Jan. 1896: 4.
The City Mission and Tract Society Journal. Feb. 1895: 2.
The Goodwill News. Nov. 1919: 6.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Accession 1980.006 was the gift of the Brooklyn Division of the Protestant Council of Churches, 1980. Accession 1980.007 was the gift of Anne Carey, 1980.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Brooklyn Division of the Protestant Council of Churches trace the history of Protestantism and missionary work in Brooklyn well into the 20th century. The bulk of the collection consists of office files dating from 1950 to 1974; however, much of the material in this collection concerns missionary work at the turn of the 19th century, and the collection dates back to 1840. Included in the collection are minutes, subject files, publications, financial records, and newspaper clippings. The collection has been arranged functionally according to seven series:
Missing Title
Related organizations
Minutes and reports
Financial records
Publications
Subject files
Scrapbooks
Photographs
Conditions Governing Access
Some of the material in Series 5, Subject files, is restricted due to issues of privacy. Please consult library staff for more information.
Related Materials
Related archival collections at the Brooklyn Historical Society:
Missing Title
1977.083, American Board of Commissioners of Foreign Missions annual meeting book, 1870
1978.153, Brooklyn Clerical Union minute books and scrapbook, 1844-1940
ARC.184, Council of Churches of the City of New York collection, 1947-1985
ARC.242, Religious philanthropic organizations of Brooklyn collection, 1828-1986
Photographs; Publications; Minutes; Scrapbooks; Financial records; Religious education of children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Protestants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Evangelistic work |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Interdenominational cooperation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Church records; Reports; Missions |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Prisons |x Missions and charities; Christian union |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Clergy |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Religious institutions |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sunday schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Theology; Religious newspapers and periodicals; Church management |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Church charities |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Church and social problems |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Brooklyn City Tract Society; Brooklyn City Mission and Tract Society; Protestant Council of the City of New York; Brooklyn Church and Mission Federation (New York, N.Y.); Protestant Council of the City of New York. Brooklyn Division
- Series 1: Related organizations (Box ARC.270 2 of 36, Box ARC.270 3 of 36)
  Scope and Contents
  The materials found in this series track organizations that worked in tandem with the Brooklyn Division and its predecessors or that were subsumed by the Brooklyn Division, most notably the Brooklyn Federation of Churches. This series is primarily composed of reports and minutes from these organizations. Most often represented in this series is the Brooklyn Federation of Churches. The series contains minutes of both the Federation as a whole and of its smaller committees. The minutes of the Federation trace the social concerns, community involvement, and organization of this group during its 12 years of existence, including the reasons behind the Federation's merger with the Brooklyn Church and Mission Society.
- Series 2: Minutes and reports, 1848-1972 (Box ARC.270 3 of 36, Box ARC.270 4 of 36, Box ARC.270 5 of 36, Box ARC.270 6 of 36, Box ARC.270 7 of 36, Box ARC.270 1 of 36, Box ARC.270 29 of 36, Box ARC.270 30 of 36, Box ARC.270 31 of 36, Box ARC.270 32 of 36)
  This series consists of minutes and reports of the Brooklyn Division and of many of the Division's predecessors. The minutes trace the histories of the Brooklyn City Tract Society, the Brooklyn City Mission and Tract Society, the Brooklyn City Mission Society, the Brooklyn Church and Mission Federation, and the Brooklyn Division of the Protestant Council of Churches. These minutes, taken either on leaves of paper or in ledgers, detail the structural composition of these organizations. Detailed here is the business aspect of each organization, including financial concerns, elections of officers, and structural changes such as amendments to the bylaws. Minute books document many of the transformations that occurred within various organizations over a period of over 100 years that led to the creation of the Brooklyn Division.
- Series 3: Financial records (Box ARC.270 7 of 36, Box ARC.270 8 of 36, Box ARC.270 33 of 36, Box ARC.270 34 of 36)
  The majority of the records in this series concern the finances of the Brooklyn Division of the Protestant Council of Churches and the Brooklyn Church and Mission Federation as a part of the Division. Included are account books, financial statements, lists of salaries, and finance committee minutes.
- Series 4: Publications, 1861-1979 (Box ARC.270 8 of 36, Box ARC.270 9 of 36)
  The publications in this series make up a small yet significant portion of the collection. This series provides significant documentation of 19th-century Protestantism and missionary work. The journals of the Brooklyn City Mission and Tract Society detail the missionary work of the Society. Originally published as the Society's annual report, the journal came to be published monthly and contained poetry, fictional stories, photographs, and reports on the Society's missionary work. Each issue focused on the report of one major missionary project, whether the Floating Bethel, the City Mission Night Shelter for the Homeless, or one of the Society's missions. Included are statistics on how many had taken advantage of a given facility, the services provided there, financial breakdowns, staffing information, and the goals of the facility. Also included in the journals are lists of officers, missionaries, and the members of the Women's Auxiliary, testimonials, and brief updates on other work in the community.
- Series 5: Subject files, 1950-1974
  The subject files make up a significant portion of the collection. Dating from 1950 to 1974, the files cover topics the Brooklyn Division was concerned with during this period, as well as files concerning the day to day running of the Division. Files include information on different parishes, the clergy volunteer program, the education committee, the 1973 United Farm Workers' Strike, and neighborhood revitalization. Many of these files contain detailed statistical analysis of the demographics of Brooklyn, gathered by the Division to determine how Protestant churches might best serve and appeal to the community. Included in the files are newspaper clippings, correspondence, pamphlets, and committee minutes. Some of the material in these files is restricted due to issues of privacy.
  - Bushwick Parish, 1963-1966 (Box ARC.270 9 of 36)
  - Bushwick Parish, 1967-1969 (Box ARC.270 10 of 36)
  - By-Laws Committee, 1960s (Box ARC.270 10 of 36)
  - Chaplains Commission, 1960-1966 (Box ARC.270 10 of 36)
  - Christian Education Department, 1962-1966 (Box ARC.270 10 of 36)
  - Christian Social Relations Department, 1960-1966 (Box ARC.270 10 of 36)
  - Christian Unity Committee, 1967 (Box ARC.270 10 of 36)
  - Church Community Associations, 1968-1969 (Box ARC.270 11 of 36)
  - Church Research and Planning Department, 1961-1965 (Box ARC.270 11 of 36)
  - Church Planning and Research Committee, 1967-1969 (Box ARC.270 11 of 36)
  - Clergy Associations: Brooklyn, 1965-1966 (Box ARC.270 11 of 36)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box ARC.270 11 of 36)
  - Correspondence: Incoming, 1969 (Box ARC.270 12 of 36)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing, 1969 (Box ARC.270 12 of 36)
  - Court consultant, 1968-1969 (Box ARC.270 12 of 36)
  - Ecumenical activity, 1966-1967 (Box ARC.270 12 of 36)
  - Evaluation Committee, 1961 (Box ARC.270 12 of 36)
  - Executive Committee, 1960-1967 (Box ARC.270 12 of 36)
  - Executive Secretary report, 1964 (Box ARC.270 12 of 36)
  - Executive Secretary, 1965-1969 (Box ARC.270 12 of 36)
  - Federation of Protestant Men, 1955-1969 (Box ARC.270 12 of 36)
  - Field Coordinator, 1969 (Box ARC.270 12 of 36)
  - Finance Committee, 1950s-1967 (Box ARC.270 12 of 36)
  - Finance Committee, 1968-1969 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Future programs and planning, 1965-1966 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Interfaith Community Services, 1966-1968 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - N.C. McDowell, 1965 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Memos, 1960-1967 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Memos - Christian Education Department, 1960-1963, 1967 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Ministers Convocation, 1963-1965 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Pastor's Bulletin, 1966 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Personnel Committee, 1960-1969 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Public Relations, 1960s (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Department of Religious Activities and Evangelism, 1964-1965 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Special Events, 1968 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Testimonial Dinner, 1964-1968 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Twin Pines Committee Minutes, 1964, 1966, 1968 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Board of Managers, 1970 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Boro Assembly, 1970 (Box ARC.270 13 of 36)
  - Boro executive staff, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Bushwick Parish, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - By-Laws, 1971 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Chaplain's Committee, 1971 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Christian Education Program, 1971 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Christian Relations Committee, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Christian Social Relations, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Church Community Association, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Church Planning and Research Committee, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Correspondence - Incoming, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Correspondence - Outgoing, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Court consultant, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Evaluation Committee, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Executive secretary, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Federation of Protestant Men, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Finance Committee, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Haitian Baptist Church, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Newsclippings - Charles Straut, 1965-1971 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Newsletter, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Personnel Committee, 1970 (Box ARC.270 14 of 36)
  - Testimonial Dinner - Steering Committee, 1970 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Bensonhurst Inter Church Council, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Board of Directors, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Board of Managers, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Borough Assembly, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Brooklyn Union Clerical Union, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Brownsville Church Task Force, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Bushwick Parish Ecumenical Association, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Christian Relations Committee, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Church Women United, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Correspondence - Outgoing, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Correspondence - Incoming, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Court Work Committee, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Executive and program staff, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Executive Committee, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Executive secretary, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Federation of Protestant Men, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Finance Task Force, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Flatbush Church Community Association, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Fort Greene, [1971] (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Hope Affair (re: Bob Hope), 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Housing, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Laymen's Convocation, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Narcotics Task Force, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Newsclippings - Charles Straut, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - New York Harriburg Defense Committee, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Office staff, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Pastoral care, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Planning Committee, 1971 (Box ARC.270 15 of 36)
  - Political Issues, [1971] (Box ARC.270 16 of 36)
  - Publicity and Public Relations, 1971 (Box ARC.270 16 of 36)
  - St. Paul's United Methodist Church, 1971 (Box ARC.270 16 of 36)
  - Testimonial Dinner, 1971 (Box ARC.270 16 of 36)
  - Twin Pines, 1971 (Box ARC.270 16 of 36)
  - Boro Assembly, 1972 (Box ARC.270 16 of 36)
  - Brooklyn Clerical Union, 1972 (Box ARC.270 16 of 36)
  - Brooklyn Coordinated Ministries, 1972 (Box ARC.270 16 of 36)
  - Brooklyn Lutheran Parish, 1971 (Box ARC.270 16 of 36)
  - Brooklyn Sunday School Union, 1972 (Box ARC.270 16 of 36)
  - Bushwick Parish, 1972 (Box ARC.270 16 of 36)
  - Chaplain's Commission, 1972 (Box ARC.270 16 of 36)
  - Christian Relations Committee, 1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Christian Social Relations Committee, 1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Church Community Association, 1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Church Women United in Brooklyn, 1969-1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Clergy Volunteer Program, Brooklyn House of Detention, 1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Clergy Volunteer Program, Brooklyn House of Detention, 1971-1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Use of this folder is restricted due to sensitive personal information.
  - Clergy Volunteer Program, Brooklyn House of Detention - Bail Fund, 1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Correspondence - Outgoing, 1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Correspondence - Incoming, 1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Council of Churches Week, 1971 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Court consultant, 1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Board of Directors, 1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Executive Committee, 1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Executive secretary, 1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Federation of Protestant Men, [1972] (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Flatbush Church Community Association, 1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Flatlands Ecumenical Committee, 1972 (Box ARC.270 17 of 36)
  - Fulton Park Urban Renewal Association, 1970, 1972 (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - Board of Managers, [1972] (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - Mid-County Church Community Association, 1970-1972 (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - Newsclippings, 1972 (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - Nominating Committee, 1970-1972 (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - Newsletters, 1970-1972 (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - Operation Bread Basket, 1971 (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - Panthers, 1970-1972 (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - Park Slope Clergy Association, 1969-1972 (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - Planning Committee: Program proposals, 1971-1972 (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - Political Issues, 1972 (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - Publicity and Public Relations, 1972 (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - St. Paul's United Methodist Church, 1971-1972 (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - Schabert and Joyner Estates, [circa 1970s] (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - South Brooklyn Clergy Association, 1970-1972 (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - Special gifts campaign, 1967-1972 (Box ARC.270 18 of 36)
  - Testimonial Dinner, 1972 (Box ARC.270 19 of 36)
  - Testimonial Dinner: Correspondence, 1972 (Box ARC.270 19 of 36)
  - Twin Pines, 1969-1972 (Box ARC.270 19 of 36)